Almost two years ago,
قبل عامين تقريباً
I was driving in my car in Germany,
كنت أقود سيارتي في ألمانـيا
and I turned on the radio.
وفتحت المذياع على إحدى المحطات
Europe at the time was in the middle
كانت أوروبا في ذلك الوقت وسط
of the Euro crisis,
أزمة اليـورو
and all the headlines were about European countries
وكانت جميع الأخبار عن الدول الأوروبـية
getting downgraded by rating agencies
التي حصلت على تقييم متـدني ومنخفض من قبل وكالات التصنيف الائتماني
in the United States.
في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
I listened and thought to myself,
استمعت الى الأخبار وقلت لنفـسي
"What are these rating agencies,
"ما هي وكالات التصنيف الائتماني
and why is everybody so upset about their work?"
ولماذا يبدو الجميع منزعجاً من عملهم؟"
Well, if you were sitting
حسنا إن كنتم بجانبي
next to me in the car that day
في السيارة ذلك اليوم
and would have told me that I would devote
وأخبرتموني أنني سأكرس
the next years to trying to reform them,
السنوات القادمة لمحاولة إصلاح ذلك،
obviously I would have called you crazy.
من الواضح أنني سأنعتكم بالجنون،
But guess what's really crazy:
ولكن خمنوا ماهو الجنون فعلاً
the way these rating agencies are run.
إنها الطريقة التي تعمل بها هذه المؤسسات،
And I would like to explain to you
وأود أن أشرح لكم
not only why it's time to change this,
أنه قد حان الوقت لنغير هذا،
but also how we can do it.
و أننا قادرون على القيام بذلك،
So let me tell you a little bit
دعوني أحدثكم قليلا
about what rating agencies really do.
بما تقوم به فعلاً هذه المؤسسات،
As you would read a car magazine
الامر أشبه بقراءة مجلة سيارات
before purchasing a new car
قبل شراء سيارة جديدة
or taking a look at a product review
أو إلقاء نظرة على عرض منتج
before deciding which kind of tablet or phone to get,
قبل الحسم في شراء أي نوع من الهواتف أو الحواسيب اللوحية،
investors are reading ratings
كذلك يقوم المستثمرون بالاطلاع على تقييمات هذه المؤسسات
before they decide in which kind of product
قبل أن يقرروا استثمار أموالهم
they are investing their money.
في منتج ما،
A rating can range from a so-called AAA,
تبدأ التقييمات من AAA،
which means it's a top-performing product,
التي تدل أنه منتج ذو أداء جيد جداً،
and it can go down to the level
وقد تصل الى مستوى
of the so-called BBB-,
يسمى BBB-
which means it's a fairly risky investment.
الذي يعني أنه استثمار محفوف بالمخاطر،
Rating agencies are rating companies.
تقوم هذه المؤسسات بتقييم الشركات،
They are rating banks.
والمصارف،
They are rating even financial products
كما تقوم بتقييم المنتجات المالية
like the infamous mortgage-backed securities.
كرسوم الرهن العقارية سيئة السمعة،
But they can also rate countries,
ولكن يمكنها أيضاً تقييم البلدان،
and these ratings are called sovereign ratings,
وتسمى هذه التقييمات بـالتقييمات السيادية،
and I would like to focus in particular
وأود أن تركزوا بالخصوص
on these sovereign ratings.
على هذه التقييمات السيادية،
And I can tell, as you're listening to me right now,
يمكنني معرفة ماتفكرون فيه،
you're thinking,
وأنتم تستمعون إلي
so why should I really care about this, right?
لماذا علي أن أهتم لهذا الشأن
Be honest.
كونوا صريحين.
Well, ratings affect you.
لهذه التقيمات تأثيرٌ عليكم.
They affect all of us.
إنها تؤثر علينا جميعاً.
If a rating agency rates a country,
عندما تقيم هذه المؤسسة بلداً من البلدان،
it basically assesses and evaluates
فإنها بالأساس تقدر وتقيم
a country's debt
ديون هذا البلد
and the ability and willingness of a country
وكذلك قدرته واستعداده
to repay its debt.
على تسديد الدين،
So if a country gets downgraded by a rating agency,
وبالتالي فإن حصل بلدٌ ما على تصنيفٍ متدن من طرف الوكالة،
the country has to pay more
فسيكون ملزماً بأداء المزيد
in order to borrow money
بغية اقتراض المال
on the international markets.
من الأسواق الدولية.
So it affects you as a citizen and as a taxpayer,
وبالتالي فهذا يؤثر فيكم كمواطنين وكدافعي ضرائب،
because you and your fellow countrymen
لأنكم أنتم ومواطنيكم
have to pony up more in order to borrow.
ستجبرون على تسديد الكثير من أجل الاقتراض.
But what if a country can't afford to pay more
ولكن ماذا سيحدث إذا عجز بلدً ما عن الأداء
because it's maybe too expensive?
بسبب كلفة الدين المرتفعة مثلاً ؟
Well, then the country has less available
سيكون البلد عاجزاً عن تمويل
for other services, like roads, schools, healthcare.
خدمات أخرى ، مثل الطرق والمدارس و الرعاية الصحية.
And this is the reason why you should care,
ولهذا يجب أن يهمكم الأمر،
because sovereign ratings affect everyone.
لأن التصنيفات السيادية تؤثر على الجميع،
And that is the reason why I believe
وهذا هو السبب في اعتقادي
they should be defined as public goods.
أنه لابد أن تكون معرفة كملكية عامة
They should be transparent, accessible,
ينبغي أن تكون شفافة وسهلة المنال،
and available to everyone at no cost.
و متاحة للجميع دون أي تكلفة.
But here's the situation:
ولكن في الواقع
the rating agency market is dominated
ثلاث وكالات فقط هي التي تستحوذ
by three players and three players only --
على مجال التصنيف الائتماني
Standard &amp; Poor's, Moody's, and Fitch --
ستاندرد اند بورز وموديز وفيتش
and we know whenever there is a market concentration,
ونعلم جيداً أنه أينما وجد تركيز اقتصادي،
there is really no competition.
فلا وجود للمنافسة هنالك،
There is no incentive to improve
ولا وجود لحافز لتحسين
the quality of your product.
جودة هذا المنتج،
And let's face it, the credit rating agencies have contributed,
دعونا نواجه الأمر، فوكالات التصنيف الائتماني هذه،
putting the global economy on the brink,
قد ساهمت في وضع الاقتصاد العالمي في الهاوية،
and yet they have to change the way they operate.
ومع ذلك عليهم أن يغيروا الطريقة التي يعملون بها.
The second point,
النقطة الثانية،
would you really buy a car
هل تريدون شراء سيارة
just based on the advice of the dealer?
استناداً فقط على نصيحة البائع؟
Obviously not, right? That would be irresponsible.
بالطبع لا ، أليس كذلك؟ سيكون ذلك أمراً غير مسؤول.
But that's actually what's going on
ولكن في الحقيقة هذا مايحدث
in the rating agency sector every single day.
في وكالات التصنيف كل يوم.
The customers of these rating agencies,
عملاء وكالات التصنيف هذه،
like countries or companies,
كالبلدان أو الشركات،
they are paying for their own ratings,
يدفعون من أجل تصنيفهم الخاص،
and obviously this is creating
و الواضح أن هذا ما يخلق
a conflict of interest.
تضارباً في المصالح .
The third point is,
و النقطة الثالثة هي ،
the rating agencies are not really telling us
وكالات التصنيف لا تطلعنا
how they are coming up with their ratings,
على الطريقة التي يتبعونها في تصنيفاتهم،
but in this day and age,
ولكن في هذا العصر،
you can't even sell a candy bar
لا يمكنك حتى بيع قطعة حلوى
without listing everything that's inside.
دون إدراج كل ما تحتويه.
But for ratings, a crucial element of our economy,
ولكن في التصنيف ، العنصر الحاسم في اقتصادنا،
we really do not know
نحن حقاً لا نعرف
what all the different ingredients are.
ما هي جميع المكونات المستعملة.
We are allowing the rating agencies
نحن نسمح لوكالات التصنيف
to be intransparent about their work,
أن تكون غير شفافة في عملها،
and we need to change this.
و نحن بحاجة إلى تغيير هذا.
I think there is no doubt that the sector
أعتقد أنه ليس هناك مكان للشك أن القطاع
needs a complete overhaul,
يحتاج الى إصلاحٍ كامل،
not just a trimming at the margins.
ليس مجرد تقليم في الهوامش.
I think it's time for a bold move.
وأعتقد أنه حان الوقت لخطوة جريئة
I think it's time to upgrade the system.
وأعتقد أنه حان الوقت لتحسين النظام.
And this is why we at the Bertelsmann Foundation
و هذا هو السبب في أننا في مؤسسة برتلسمان
have invested a lot of time and effort
قد استثمرنا الكثير من الوقت والجهد
thinking about an alternative for the sector.
للتفكير في بديل لهذا القطاع.
And we have developed the first model
و قمنا بتطوير أول نموذج
for a nonprofit rating agency for sovereign risk,
لوكالة غير ربحية لتقييم المخاطر السيادية ،
and we call it by its acronym, INCRA.
و نسميها اختصاراً INCRA.
INCRA would make a difference
INCRA ستحدث فرقاً
to the current system
في النظام الحالي
by adding another nonprofit player to the mix.
بإضافة عاملٍ غير ربحي إلى الميدان.
It would be based on a nonprofit model
وسوف يستند على نموذج غير ربحي
that would be based on a sustainable endowment.
الذي سيكون أساسه منح مستدامة.
The endowment would create income
هذه المنح قد تخلق دخلاً
that would allow us to run the operation,
الذي من شأنه أن يسمح لنا بـالعمل،
to run the rating agency,
لتشغيل وكالة التصنيف،
and it would also allow us
الشيء الذي سيسمح لنا أيضاً
to make our ratings publicly available.
بـجعل تقييماتنا متاحة للعامة .
But this is not enough to make a difference, right?
ولكن هذا لا يكفي لإحداث الفرق ، أليس كذلك؟
INCRA would also be based on
ستستند INCRA أيضاً على
a very, very clear governance structure
هيكل حكمٍ واضحٌ جداً
that would avoid any conflict of interest,
والذي من شأنه أن يجنبنا أي تضارب في المصالح،
and it would include many stakeholders from society.
وستتضمن عدداً من الفاعلين في المجتمع.
INCRA would not only be a European
INCRA لن تكون فقط وكالة تصنيفٍ أوروبيةً
or an American rating agency,
أو أمريكيةً
it would be a truly international one,
بل ستكون دوليةً،
in which, in particular, the emerging economies
والتي ستتمتع فيها الاقتصادات الناشئة على وجه الخصوص
would have an equal interest, voice and representation.
على الصوت و التمثيل كغيرها من الاقتصادات.
The second big difference that INCRA would make is
الفرق الكبيرالثاني الذي ستحدثه INCRA هو
that would it base its sovereign risk assessment
أن تقييم المخاطر السيادية سيعتمد
on a broader set of indicators.
على مجموعة أوسع من المؤشرات.
Think about it that way.
فكروا في الأمر بهذه الطريقة.
If we conduct a sovereign rating,
إذا أنجزنا تصنيفاً سيادياً ما ،
we basically take a look at
فإننا بالأساس قمنا بالقاء نظرةٍ على
the economic soil of a country,
التربة الاقتصادية لهذا البلد،
its macroeconomic fundamentals.
على توازناته الماكرو اقتصادية
But we also have to ask the question,
لكن السؤال الذي يجب أن نطرحه أيضاً هو :
who is cultivating the economic soil
من الذي يقوم بـزراعة التربة الاقتصادية
of a country, right?
لبلدٍ ما، أليس كذلك؟
Well, a country has many gardeners,
حسناً ، يمتلك كل بلد العديد من البستانين ،
and one of them is the government,
والحكومة هي واحدةٌ منهم ،
so we have to ask the question,
لذلك يجب أن نطرح هذا السؤال،
how is a country governed?
كيف يبدو حكم البلد ؟
How is it managed?
كيف تتم إدارته؟
And this is the reason why we have developed
و هذا هو السبب في أننا طورنا
what we call forward-looking indicators.
ما نسميه مؤشرات تطلعية .
These are indicators that give you
هذه هي المؤشرات التي تعطيك
a much better read about
قراءة أفضل بكثير عن
the socioeconomic development of a country.
التنمية الاجتماعية والاقتصادية في البلد .
I hope you would agree it's important for you to know
وآمل أن تتفقوا معي أنه من المهم أن تعرفوا
if your government is willing to invest in renewable energy and education.
إذا كانت حكومتكم على استعداد للاستثمار في مجال الطاقة المتجددة والتعليم.
It's important for you to know
أنه من المهم بالنسبة لكم أن تعرفوا
if the government of your country
إذا كانت حكومة بلدكم
is able to manage a crisis,
قادرةٌ على إدارة أزمة،
if the government is finally able to implement
إذا كانت الحكومة قادرة على تنفيذ
the reforms that it's promised.
الإصلاحات التي وعدت بها .
For example, if INCRA would rate
على سبيل المثال، إذا أعطت INCRA تقييماً
South Africa right now,
لجنوب أفريقيا في الوقت الراهن،
of course we would take a very, very close look
فبالطبع سنلقي نظرة قريبة جداً
at the youth unemployment of the country,
على نسبة بطالة الشباب في البلد،
the highest in the world.
الأعلى في العالم.
If over 70 percent of a country's population
إذا كان أكثر من 70 في المئة من سكان البلد
under the age of 35 is unemployed,
تحت سن الخامسة والثلاثين عاطلين عن العمل ،
of course this has a huge impact on the economy
بالطبع سيكون لهذا تأثيرٌ كبيرٌ على الاقتصاد
today and even more so in the future.
في الحاضر وقد يكون أكثر من ذلك في المستقبل.
Well, our friends at Moody's,
حسنا، في وكالة موديز ،
Standard &amp; Poor's, and Fitch will tell us
و ستاندرد اند بورز ، وفيتش سيخبروننا
we would take this into account as well.
أنهم يأخذون ذلك في الحسبان أيضاً.
But guess what? We do not know
ولكن خمنوا ماذا ؟ نحن لا نعرف
exactly how they will take this into account.
بالضبط كيف سيأخذون هذا في الحسبان.
And this leads me to the third big difference
و هذا سيقودني إلى الفرق الكبير الثالث
that INCRA would make.
الذي ستحدثه INCRA .
INCRA would not only release its ratings
INCRA لن تكشف فقط كيف تقوم بـتصنيفاتها
but it would also release its indicators
بل ستكشف أيضاً عن المؤشرات
and methodology.
وعن المنهجية المتبعة.
So in contrast to the current system,
لذلك وبعكس النظام الحالي،
INCRA would be fully transparent.
INCRA ستكون شفافةً تماماً.
So in a nutshell,
لذلك باختصار ،
INCRA would offer an alternative
INCRA ستقدم بديلاً
to the current system of the big three rating agencies
للنظام الحالي المتمثل في وكالات التصنيف الثلاثة الكبار
by adding a new, nonprofit player to the mix
عن طريق إضافة ، عامل جديد لا يهدف للربح إلى الميدان
that would increase the competition,
والذي سيؤدي الى زيادة المنافسة،
it would increase the transparency of the sector,
والى الرفع من شفافية هذا القطاع،
and it would also increase the quality.
و أيضا الى زيادة جودة الخدمة.
I can tell that sovereign ratings
أستطيع أن أقول أن التصنيفات السيادية
may still look to you like this very small piece
لا تزال تبدو لكم كقطعةٍ صغيرةٍ جداً
of this very complex global financial world,
من هذا النظام المالي العالمي المعقد جداً،
but I tell you it's a very important one,
لكنها مهمة جداً،
and a very important one to fix,
وتعتبر من الاشياء الواجب إصلاحها،
because sovereign ratings affect all of us,
لأن التصنيفات السيادية تؤثر علينا جميعاً ،
and they should be addressed and should be defined
و ينبغي أن تكون معرفةً
as public goods.
كملكية عامة.
And this is why we are testing our model right now,
و هذا هو السبب الذي دفعنا لاختبار نموذجنا في الوقت الراهن،
and why we are trying to find out if it can
ومحاولة معرفة ما إذا كان يمكن
bring together a group of able and willing actors
جمع مجموعة من الممثلين المستعدين
to bring INCRA to life.
لتقديم INCRA إلى الحياة.
I truly believe building up INCRA
أعتقد حقاً أن تأسيس INCRA
is in everyone's interest,
في مصلحة الجميع ،
and that we have the unique opportunity right now
ولدينا الآن الفرصة المميزة
to turn INCRA into a cornerstone
لنحول INCRA إلى حجر الزاوية
of a new, more inclusive financial system.
لنظام مالي جديد أكثر شمولاً.
Because for way too long,
لأنه مضى وقتٌ طويلٌ،
we have left the big financial players on their own.
على تركنا الفاعلين الماليين الكبار لوحدهم.
It's time to give them some company.
وقد حان الوقت لإعطائهم بعض الصحبة.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
( تصفيق )